Finding Aid to the Long Point Gallery Records, 1959-1999, bulk 1976-1998, in the Archives of American Art AAA.longpoin
Archives of American Art
Long Point Gallery records
bulk 1976-1998
1959-1999
AAA.longpoin
Archives of American Art
7.1 Linear feet
The records of the Long Point Gallery measure 7.1 linear feet and date from 1959 to 1999, bulk 1976 to 1998. The collection documents the history of the gallery through administrative records, guest books, correspondence, exhibition files, artists' files, financial records, printed material, and photographic materials.
Long Point Gallery.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated in 1999 and 2013 by the Long Point Gallery via Rosalind Pace, former Director.
Biographical/Historical note
Long Point Gallery (est. 1977, closed 1998) was a cooperative art gallery in Provincetown, Massachusetts. The gallery operated in the American Legion building during the summer seasons as an artist cooperative. Members contributed financially, as well as artistically, enabling the promotion and preparation of exhibitions throughout the summer. The founding members were Varujan Boghosian, Fritz Bultman, Carmen Cicero, Sideo Fromboluti, Edward Giobbi, Budd Hopkins, Rick Klauber, Leo Manso, Robert Motherwell, Paul Resika, Judith Rothschild, Sidney Simon, Nora Speyer, and Tony Vevers. Later in the gallery's history Robert Beauchamp, Paul Bowen, Gilbert Franklin, Dimitri Hadzi, Renate Ponsold, and Michael Mazur also became members. Some notable friends of the gallery were Nassos Daphnis, Jack Tworkov, and Myron Stout. The gallery's first director was Rick Librizzi.
The Long Point Gallery gained a reputation for showing progressive, expressionist and abstract paintings and sculptures that veered away from the traditional tourist scenes of Cape Cod. During the 1980's, Provincetown was becoming a popular tourist destination, which caused real estate values to climb. Fortunately, members of the cooperative were able to afford the rising costs and remain in Provincetown allowing the gallery to become a fixture within the community. The gallery often held dual exhibits featuring two artists who presented their artwork individually. Other exhibitions include "Homeric Themes" (1987), "Myth & Ritual" (1989), "From the Studio Wall" (1990), "A Long Point Portfolio" (1991), "Keyworks" (1991), "Those Lovely Golden Thighs" (1991), and "A Story to Tell" (1996). Members also represented the Long Point Gallery in exhibitions at the Fine Arts Work Center (FAWC), the Cape Museum of Fine Arts (CMFA), the Archives of American Art, and exhibitions in Europe. For over 20 years, the Long Point Gallery was the site of art exhibitions, poetry readings, musical performances, and parties until its closing in 1998.
In 1998, the American Legion building was sold at a price that was too high for the gallery to continue in the same location. The advanced ages and deaths of a few members prior to the sale of the building contributed to the members' decision to dissolve the gallery, which was under the direction of Rosalind Pace at the time of closing.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the Long Point Gallery measure 7.1 linear feet and date from 1959 to 1999, bulk 1976 to 1998. The collection documents the history of the gallery through administrative records, guest books, correspondence, exhibition files, artists' files, financial records, printed material, and photographic materials.
Administrative records consist of legal documents, contracts, mailing lists, price lists, membership files, correspondence, meeting minutes, gallery history, projects files, and one videocassette of the Long Point Gallery dinner filmed by Renate Ponsold Motherwell in 1993. Guest books document the signatures and salutations of attendees at gallery exhibitions. Correspondence is with artists, organizations, and gallery customers. Exhibition files contain correspondence, press releases, articles, and exhibition announcements. Artists' files consist of news clippings, exhibition records, price lists, and correspondence. Financial records contain bills, receipts, deposits, financial reports, gallery sales, and records for the transport of artwork. Printed material includes news clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, press releases, obituaries, publications, souvenirs, and posters signed by the artists. Photographic materials include slides and printed photographs of artwork, artists, exhibitions, parties, and candid moments. Overall the collection documents the activities of artist members, including Varujan Boghosian, Fritz Bultman, Carmen Cicero, Sideo Fromboluti, Edward Giobbi, Budd Hopkins, Rick Klauber, Leo Manso, Robert Motherwell, Paul Resika, Judith Rothschild, Sidney Simon, Nora Speyer, Tony Vevers, Robert Beauchamp, Paul Bowen, Gilbert Franklin, Dimitri Hadzi, Renate Ponsold, and Michael Mazur.
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1976-1999 (1.5 linear ft.; Box 1-2)
Series 2: Guest Books, 1986-1998 (7 folders; Box 2)
Series 3: Correspondence, 1979-1998 (0.8 linear ft.; Box 2-3)
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 1959-1998, bulk 1972-1998 (0.6 linear ft.; Box 3-4)
Series 5: Artists' Files, 1963-1997 (0.8 linear ft.; Box 4)
Series 6: Financial Records, 1976-1998 (0.8 linear ft.; Box 5)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1972-1998 (0.8 linear ft.; Box 5-6, OV 8)
Series 8: Photographic Materials, 1972-1998 (1.5 linear ft.; Box 6-7)
Beauchamp, Robert, 1923-; Boghosian, Varujan; Bultman, Fritz, 1919-1985; Cicero, Carmen, 1926-; Franklin, Gilbert, 1919-; Fromboluti, Sideo, 1921-; Giobbi, Edward; Hadzi, Dimitri, 1921-2006; Hopkins, Budd, 1931-; Manso, Leo; Mazur, Michael, 1935-2009; Motherwell, Robert; Ponsold, Renate; Resika, Paul; Rothschild, Judith; Simon, Sidney, 1917-1997; Speyer, Nora; Vevers, Tony; Art galleries, Cooperative; Artists--Massachusetts--Provincetown; Photographs; Video recordings; Visitors' books
- Administrative Records, 1976-1999; Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Scope and Contents note
  Administrative records contain price lists, meeting minutes, appraisals, mailing lists for event invitiations, an appointment book, contracts, lists of collectors, and a history and bibliography of the Long Point Gallery. This series also contains files on contributions and gifts including documents regarding 12 prints that were donated to the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston and Robert Beauchamp's bequest of a set of works on paper to Long Point Gallery. The Judith Rothschild Foundation file includes a color photograph of Rothschild in her studio along with receipt of delivery paperwork, correspondence, and press releases. Other notable records are the original signatures for several of the Long Point members and one videocassette of the Long Point Gallery dinner filmed by Renate Ponsold Motherwell in 1993.
  - Appointment Book, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Appraisals, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Attendance Tally, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Beauchamp Bequest, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Collector Lists, circa 1977, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Completed Consignment Forms, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Contributions and Gifts, circa 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Director's Responsibilities and Contract, circa 1980-1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ed's Dinner, 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Independent Contractors, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Information for Gallery Attendants, circa 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Judith Rothschild Foundation, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lease, 1979-1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Long Point Bibliography, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Long Point Brochure, circa 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Long Point Book Proposal, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Long Point Gallery Dinner, 1993; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Long Point Group Projects, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Long Point History, 1979-1987 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Long Point Party, circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Long Point Print Portfolio, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mailing List of Artists and Collectors, circa 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1976-1998 (Box 1, Folder 26-30)
  - Members' Biographies, 1987-1997 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Member Dues, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Member Signatures, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous Business, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, Gift, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - New Members Party, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - PR Mailing List, circa 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Price Lists, 1978-1992 (Box 1, Folder 38-46)
  - Price Lists, 1993-1998 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Price Lists and Notes, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Price Lists and Inventory, circa 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Price Lists, Tyler Graphics, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Press Releases, 1977-1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Provincetown Arts, circa 1985-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Resumes of Members, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Season Schedules, circa 1980-1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Tax Exemption, 1981-1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Updates, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Guest Books, 1986-1998; Series 2; 7 Folders Box 2
  Guest books include seven books that are arranged chonologically by year. They contain the signatures and salutations of visitors to the Long Point Gallery from around the world. The pages of the books are labeled with dates and exhibition titles.
  - Guest Book, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Guest Book, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Guest Book, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Guest Book, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Guest Book, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Guest Book, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Guest Book, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, 1979-1998; Series 3; 0.8 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Correspondence contains a mixture of original and photocopied correspondence between Long Point and other art galleries, collectors, customers, members, and art related organizations. This series may also contain price lists, notes, articles, and press releases that were attached to letters. A bulk of the correspondence is business related but more personal letters to and from artist members and gallery staff are scattered throughout the series.
  - Correspondence, 1980-1987 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Exhibition Files, bulk 1972-1998; 1959-1998; Series 4; 0.6 Linear feet Box 3-4
  Arrangement note
  Folders are arranged chonologically by exhibition year.
  Exhibition files document over 50 exhibitions held at the Long Point Gallery, the Fine Arts Work Center (FAWC), the Cape Museum of Fine Arts (CMFA), the Cultural Festival in Prague, Czech Republic, and the "A Long Point Portfolio" exhibit at the Belltable Arts Centre in Limerick, Ireland. Long Point often held dual exhibits where two artists showed their work simultaneously. Dual exhibitions are indicated in this finding aid with exhibition titles containing two artists names. Files may include correspondence, notes, news clippings, printed material, and price lists related to each exhibition.
  - Invitationals, 1978-1990 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "A Selection of Work by Former Fellows of the Fine Arts Work Center, Provincetown" (1980) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Reading at Long Point, Rosalind Price, circa 1981 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Bowen/Summer's Work" (1984), 1984-1994 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "Tribute to Stanley Kunitz" (1985), 1959; 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "Homeric Themes" (1987), 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Sensibility of the Artist" (1987), circa 1987 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - "Tony Vevers/Ed Giobbi" (1987), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - "Opposites/Artists' Studios" (1988) (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "75: A Celebration" (1989), 1972-1989 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
  - "Myth & Ritual" (1989) (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "Sideo Fromboluti/Tony Vevers" (1989) (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "Sidney Simon/Leo Manso" (1989) (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Varujan Boghosian/Edward Giobbi" (1990) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "From the Studio Wall"(1990) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "From the Studio Wall"(1990), Piero-The Talisman (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Squares"(1990) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "A Long Point Portfolio"(1991), Belltable Arts Center (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Budd Hopkins & Sidney Simon"(1991) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Cape Museum Exhibition"(1991), 1990-1998 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Keyworks"(1991), circa 1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Sixth Annual Art in the Garden"(1991), 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Those Lovely Golden Thighs"(1991) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Summer's Work"(1992), Long Point Poster (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Masterworks"(1993) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Cultural Festival, Prague (1994) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Ghosts: Poets & Artists"(1994), circa 1994 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - "Secrets"(1995), circa 1995 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - "Sideo Fromboluti/Paul Resika"(1995), circa 1995 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "A Story to Tell"(1996), circa 1996 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - "Eros/Michael Mazur, Blue"(1996), circa 1996 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Anniversary Season Invitational Show (1997), circa 1997 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "Provincetown Papers: Selections from New Collections"(1997), Archives of American Art, circa 1997 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - "Tribute to Long Point"(1998), CMFA, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - "Long Point Gallery at FAWC"(1998), circa 1998 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Artists' Files, 1963-1997; Series 5; 0.8 Linear feet Box 4
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by the artists' last name.
  Artists' files consist of documents pertaining to the members of Long Point Gallery. These files may contain correspondence, price lists, printed material, notes, resumes, and photographs of artwork. Files for Robert Motherwell total nine folders with six folders containing pricing and inventory information on his prints.
  - Beauchamp, Robert, circa 1995 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Berger, Arthur, circa 1986 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Cicero, Carmen, circa 1971-1985 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Hadzi, Dimitri, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Hopkins, Budd, circa 1972-1988 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Manso, Leo, circa 1979-1993 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Motherwell, Robert, circa 1979-1991 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Motherwell, Robert, Articles, circa 1979-1991 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Motherwell, Robert, Prices and Sales, 1983-1986 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Motherwell, Robert, Prints and Price Lists, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Motherwell, Robert, Prints, 1991-1997; 1985 (Box 4, Folder 33-37)
  - Resika, Paul, circa 1978-1988 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Rothschild, Judith, circa 1981-1993 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Rothschild, Judith, Printed Material, circa 1975-1992 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Simon, Sidney, circa 1963-1989 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Speyer, Nora, circa 1978-1996 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Vevers, Tony, circa 1969-1989 (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Financial Records, 1976-1998; Series 6; 0.8 Linear feet Box 5
  Financial records consist of financial reports, bills and receipts, expense reports, ledgers, gallery sales, and several folders containing records on shipping and the transportation of artwork by truck. Files may also contain related correspondence, price lists, and notes.
  - Financial Records, 1976-1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Accounts, 1988-1994 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Bills, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Bills and Paid Receipts, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Bogel & Moloy, Expenses, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Business (1988), 1978-1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Deposits, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Expenses, 1981-1994 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Financial Report (1994 Season), 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Gallery Sales, 1978-1998 (Box 5, Folder 10-18)
  - Gallery Sales, Ledger, 1987-1997 (Box 5, Folder 19-21)
  - Long Point Receipts, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Payments for Purchases of Art, 1995-1998 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Shipping, circa 1991-1995 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Tax Information, 1987-1989 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Truck Expenses, Receipts and Invoices, 1980-1985 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Truck Transport, 1987-1995 (Box 5, Folder 27-32)
- Printed Material, 1972-1998; Series 7; 0.8 Linear feet Box 5-6, OV 8
  Printed material mainly consists of original and photocopied news articles regarding Long Point members and exhibitions. Also included are exhibition announcements and catalogs, obituaries, and several arts publications. Reproductions include notecards showing artwork, photocopies of a sketch of a woman's face, and one poster. Other posters signed by the artists are included in oversized material.
  - Antiques & Arts, 1994; 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - "Blackbird", Poem, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Cape Cod Times, 1998; 1996 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1977-1997 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1985; 1979 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - News Clippings, 1972; 1977-1988 (Box 5, Folder 38-41)
  - News Clippings, 1989-1998; undated (Box 6, Folder 1-6)
  - Obituaries, 1990-1996 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Press Coverage: The Long Point Gallery Provincetown, 1976-1990 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Press Releases, 1978-1998; undated (Box 6, Folder 9-12)
  - Provincetown Advocate, 1977; 1998 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Provincetown Arts, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Record of Exhibitions, 1977-1998 (Box 6, Folder 15-16)
  - Reproductions, circa 1977-1986; Oversize material housed in Box 8 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Souvenirs, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Oversize Reproductions from Box 6, Folder 17 (Box 8)
- Photographic Materials, 1972-1998; Series 8; 1.5 Linear feet Box 6-7
  Photographic material consists of prints, negatives, and slides that document various parties, exhibitions, artwork, and Long Point artists. Included are photographs of the artists behind the scenes at exhibitions assisting with hanging artwork and gallery preparations. Group photographs of artist members taken by Renate Ponsold and Joel Meyerowitz are included, as well as individual portraits of several of the artists. Photographs and slides of exhibitions include individual photographs of the artwork, views of the exhibition space, and exhibition attendees. The bulk of the photographs and slides are labeled.
  - Photographs of Artists, 1972-1998 (Box 6, Folder 19-20)
  - Photograph Album, circa 1982-1991 (Box 6, Folder 21-22)
  - Exhibitions and Events, circa 1987-1993; 1977 (Box 6, Folder 23-26)
  - Exhibitions and Events, circa 1995-1998 (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
  - Long Point Portfolio, circa 1998 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1988-1993 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Negative and Contact Prints of Artwork and Exhibitions, circa 1993 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Slides of Artwork and Exhibitions, circa 1982-1994 (Box 7, Folder 10-13)